Guide to the American Dance Festival Records, circa 1924-1985, bulk 1934-1977 ADF.015
American Dance Festival Archives
American Dance Festival records
circa 1924-1988, bulk 1934-1977
American Dance Festival Archives
American Dance Festival
ADF.015
89.05 Linear Feet
The American Dance Festival is a non-profit organization committed to serving the needs of dance, dancers, choreographers, and professionals in dance-related fields. It presents a summer festival of modern dance performances and educational programs, hosts community outreach activities, and sponsors numerous projects in the humanities. Its mission is to create and present new dance works, preserve the modern dance heritage, build wider national and international audiences and enhance public understanding and appreciation for modern dance, and provide training and education for dancers and choreographers. Contains correspondence, lists, administrative materials, memoranda, contracts, legal documents, financial records, class schedules, teaching materials, student records, clippings, press releases, publicity materials, brochures, tickets, posters, and other printed materials created by or related to the American Dance Festival.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Please contact the American Dance Festival Archives (adf@americandancefestival.org) to arrange for use of these materials.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, the American Dance Festival Archives permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
Records, such as search committee files or others pertaining to employment where individuals are identified, are closed for 70 years.
Historical Note
The American Dance Festival is a non-profit organization committed to serving the needs of dance, dancers, choreographers, and professionals in dance-related fields. It presents a summer festival of modern dance performances and educational programs, hosts community outreach activities, and sponsors numerous projects in the humanities. Its mission is to create and present new dance works, preserve the modern dance heritage, build wider national and international audiences and enhance public understanding and appreciation for modern dance, and provide training and education for dancers and choreographers.
The American Dance Festival traces its origins to the Bennington School of Dance, founded in 1934 in Bennington, Vermont by several notable figures in the emerging art of modern dance: Martha Graham, Hanya Holm, Doris Humphrey, and Charles Weidman. The school, led by Martha Hill, allowed choreographers to experiment and teach dance techniques. A performance series, held in conjunction with the school, provided the choreographers with opportunities to present their newly created works. For one season, in 1939, the festival was held at Mills College in Oakland, California, but returned to Bennington the following year. Beginning in 1948, the festival was held at Connecticut College, and in 1977, the decision was made to move it to Duke University in Durham, North Carolina.
Collection Overview
Contains correspondence, lists, administrative materials, memoranda, contracts, legal documents, financial records, class schedules, teaching materials, student records, clippings, press releases, publicity materials, brochures, tickets, posters, and other printed materials created by or related to the American Dance Festival before the decision to move to Durham, North Carolina, in the fall of 1977.
Choreography -- United States.; Dance -- United States.; Modern Dance -- United States.; American Dance Festival.; Bennington School of the Dance.; Connecticut College American Dance Festival.
- Administration, circa 1924-1981
  - ADF Store and Merchandise, 1962-1977, 5 folders (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Contains correspondence, inventory lists, tee-shirt designs, order forms, and administrative papers related to the sale of merchandise during the festival and the management of the store at the theater and summer offices.
    Arranged chronologically.
  - Administrative Assistant, 1958-1977, 27 folders (Box 1)
    Arrangement
    Contains administrative materials, correspondence, form letters, memoranda, mailing lists, mailings information, and listings of secretarial duties. In the 1960s, administrative assistants were secretaries working directly under the director. In later years, as the festival's administration became more complex, multiple administrative assistants were added and their duties were expanded beyond secretaries. Assistants included:
    Constance Carney, 1958
    Olive Hersant, 1963-1966
    Faith Gulick, 1964-1965
    Marjorie Chapman, 1967-1971
    Kay McGrath, 1971
    Also included are files for Lisa Booth, Assistant to Charles Reinhart in New York, 1972-1977.
  - Administrative Director, 1969-1977, 20 folders (Box 1)
    Contains administrative materials, correspondence, form letters, meeting notes and transcripts, newspaper clippings, drafts, messages, short notes, and memos, signed petitions, staff handbook, brochures, press releases, and a listing of statistics. Materials contain correspondence and documents written to and from the Administrative Director and the Administrative Assistant and the Director's office concerning daily activities, responsibilities and instructions as well as personal notes. Administrative director was a staff position from 1969 to 1993. Beginning in 1969, Charles Reinhart's first year as Director, an administrative director, a coordinator, an administrator, or an operations manager worked with Charles Reinhart and Martha Myers, the Dean, to coordinate the workings of ADF's school and festival. The Administrative Directors were:
    Robert Hale and C. Fred Grimsey (Administrators), 1969
    Olive Johns (Administrator), 1970
    Kay McGrath (Administrator), 1971-1973
    Ceilia Halstead and Cordette Grimsey (Coordinators), 1974-1975
    Mary Jane Inram and Lisa Booth (Administrators), 1976
    Lisa Booth (Administrative Director), 1977-1980
  - Archives, 1948-1978 and undated, 0.41 Linear Feet (Box 1)
    Contains correspondence, donation acknowledgements, form letters, sales notices, administrative materials, notes and memoranda, identification cards, rental agreements, photograph schedules, telegrams, ADF archives inventories, and a file storage survey of ADF files at Connecticut College, documenting ADF archival activities (except Labanotation and the Film Notation project), even when there was no formal archives program. Also included is correspondence between ADF and other institutions, such as the New York Performing Arts Library, regarding requests for ADF materials for other dance collections.
    - Documentation, 1949-1974 and undated, 6 folders (Box 1)
      Contains information and correspondence about photographers and videographers who actively documented ADF activities, with the exception of personnel related information, such as hiring and firing correspondence. It also includes release forms and information and transcripts of oral histories. The oral histories include a 1959 group interview on the subject of the first year at Bennington with several people including the Limons, the Lloyds, Louis Horst, and Bessie Schonberg.
      - Interview Notes: Martha Hill (Box 1)
      - Interview Notes: Sophie Maslow (Box 1)
      - Interview Notes: Jeanette Schlottman Roosevelt (Box 1)
      - Interview Notes: Theodora Wiesner (Box 1)
      - Oral History: First Year at Bennington, July 1959 (Box 1)
      - Photographer, 1949-1974 (Box 1)
    - Historical Facts, 1948-1966, 1 folders (Box 1)
      Contains information compiled by various ADF staff to document important ongoing events in ADF history such as premieres and commissions.
      - American Dance Festival Premieres, 1948-1966 (Box 1)
    - Preservation, 1953-1978, 4 folders (Box 1)
      Contains materials concerning the administration and preservation of the collection. Some correspondence concerns other repositories collecting ADF materials. Includes correspondence with other dance collection repositories, such as NYPL and Ohio State University, regarding the reproduction of films resulting from the Film and Notation Project for their own collections.
      - Preservation, 1953-1962 (Box 1)
      - Preservation, 1966-1973 (Box 1)
      - Preservation, Doris Humphrey Costume, 1970-1971 (Box 1)
      - Preservation, Records at Connecticut, 1976-1978 (Box 1)
    - Usage, 1956-1977, 3 folders (Box 1)
      Contains materials concerning reference services by the ADF Archives and use of archival documents. Consists primarily of correspondence between archivists and patrons, even before ADF had an archival program. Also includes forms and correspondence regarding film rentals for choreographic reconstruction (circa 1965-1969).
  - Bennington College and Mills College, 1934-1942, 2 folders (Box 1)
    Contains correspondence and notes from annual reports including schedules, program information, and general summaries that document ADF's working relationship with Bennington College and Mills College as host institutions. Also includes research notes from various sources detailing information about the School of the Dance from 1934 to 1942.
  - Board of Directors, 1975-1977, 4 folders (Box 1)
    Contains meeting minutes and correspondence related to the American Dance Festival Board of Directors, including correspondence from Charles Reinhart inviting Betty Ford to become the Honorary Chairman of the Board of Directors. The Board of Directors was established during the first meeting of the incorporators of the American Dance Festival, Inc. on July 31, 1975. Charles L. Reinhart, Martha Myers, and Elizabeth Booth were nominated and elected by the incorporators.
  - Box Office, 1948-1977 and undated (Box 1)
    - Complementary tickets, 1949-1977, 22 folders (Box 1)
      Contains lists of people, including critics and VIPs, issued complementary tickets. Also includes administrative correspondence and notes, along with correspondence to and from those who were issued tickets, as well as form letters regarding festival schedules, form letters outlining complementary ticket policy, and faculty, staff, and student ticket sign-up sheets.
    - Group Sales, 1962-1977, 13 folders (Box 1)
      Contains correspondence, form letters, and festival scheduling information regarding group ticket sales, which were primarily discounted sales to businesses and non-profit organizations.
    - House, 1948-1977, 28 folders (Box 2)
      Contains seating charts and pricing information, administrative materials, correspondence, usher and ticket taker lists, usher information sheets, application forms, box office schedules, box office summaries, complementary ticket sign-up sheets, concessions information, form letters, and payment and expenses information.
    - Interns, 1967, 1 folders (Box 2)
      Contains payroll and scheduling information pertaining to the box office internship.
    - Manager, 1948-1977, 28 folders (Box 2)
      Contains correspondence, memos, form letters, administrative materials, ticket policy information, schedules, subscriber and single ticket requests and payment materials, ticket samples, seating plans and pricing information, ticket order forms, ticket sales locations, complementary ticket policy forms, discounted ticket information, box officer managers' final reports, budget information, box office manager application information, hotel information, and Ticketron contract materials.
    - Reports, 1949-1977, 33 folders (Box 2)
      Contains box office reports, administrative materials, seating charts, receipts, and correspondence. Includes information such as the number of tickets sold for each seating price for each show and the gross and net income of each performance. Correspondence includes box office policies, estimates of profits, and ticket returns.
    - Single tickets, 1963-1977, 13 folders (Box 2)
      Contains correspondence, forms, subscription forms, student and faculty lists, listings of ticket purchases, and administrative materials concerning single ticket sales and buyers.
    - Subscriptions, 1962-1976, 7 folders (Box 2)
      Contains correspondence to and from subscribers, printed items, seating charts, forms, and administrative materials concerning subscriptions and subscribers.
    - Ticket Forms and Brochures, 1949-1977, 30 folders (Box 2)
      Contains ticket order forms, event notices, and season brochures.
    - Tickets, 1955-1977 and undated, 13 folders (Box 2)
      Contains performance tickets.
  - Community Development and Public Affairs, 1948-1977, 1.25 Linear Feet (Box 3)
    Contains materials on a variety of projects that involved bringing dance and other arts programs to the public, including contacts with government officials and arts patrons in attempts to find and continue support for dance and the arts. Also includes materials regarding classes held at Connecticut College that were open to non-Connecticut College students, such as the Folk and Square Dance class, offered during the summer festival, and children's modern dance classes and adult elementary ballet and modern dance classes offered during the academic year. Includes correspondence and materials regarding classes and workshops held as a part of the Community Outreach Program, established in 1969 under Walter Nicks to involve the community in dance. Dance and movement classes were offered to mothers and young children, teenagers, and the elderly. Also includes material regarding Friends of ADF, an organization formed in 1976 to generate income for the festival and to bring the festival and community closer together.
    Arranged chronologically and alphabetically by subject.
  - Development and Fundraising, 1948-1981 (Box 4)
    Contains materials relating to ADF's search for and development of possible funding sources.
    - Individual Donors, 1948-1977, 42 folders (Box 4)
      Contains correspondence, drafts, form letters, administrative materials, sponsors/patrons lists, receipts, lists of complementary tickets, ticket order forms, and donor solicitation letters and forms. Contains correspondence to and from individuals making donations and lists of donors receiving complementary tickets.
      Arranged chronologically and then alphabetically by subject or donor name.
    - Foundations and Funding Organizations, 1948-1977, 2.25 Linear Feet (Box 4)
      Contains correspondence, publicity materials, administration materials, schedules, grant information, summary reports, and newspaper clippings. Groups contacted with funding requests included educational institutions, state and federal government organizations, and private corporations. Of interest are materials regarding various Ford Foundation grants including the 1972-1973 grant funding the ADF Repertory Company and the 1971-1976 National Endowment of the Arts funding for the Dance Critics Conference. Materials overlap with Community Development series, and in kind donations from local organizations are filed there.
      Arranged alphabetically by organization name and then chronologically.
      - A-N (Box 4)
      - N-W (Box 5)
    - Development Office, 1948-1977, 0.25 Linear Feet (Box 6)
      Contains correspondence, administrative materials, potential donors, form letters, budgets, publicity materials, schedules, and lists of grants received. Materials include correspondence regarding funding suggestions and publicity materials for a 1974 panel on government funding and the drive to find matching funds to keep ADF at Connecticut College during the summer of 1977.
  - Directors' Files, circa 1924-1977 (Box 6)
    - Martha Hill, circa 1940-1969 (Box 6)
      Biographical / Historical
      Martha Hill, dance teacher and administrator, was a director of the Bennington summer school. From 1931 until 1951, she was a member of the dance faculty at Bennington and of the Department of Physical Education of the School of Education of New York University. In 1951 she became head of the new dance department of the Juilliard School in New York. In 1953, she became "advisory" co-director of the festival, leaving Ruth Bloomer as director. Though she no longer headed the administration, Hill remained an active member of the board of directors for the dance school and the festival.
      Contains teaching materials, schedules, correspondence, budget information, recommendations for the ADF, in-house materials, a transcript, a telegram, advertising materials, and form letters. Of interest are the 1947 planning materials for the 1948 School of the Dance. These materials include information on locations, budget, and classes. Also, a 1966 form letter urging "Colleagues in Dance" to write to their congressmen to encourage congressional support of dance as a performing art and materials on the 1969 presentation of an honorary doctorate to Martha Hill Davies by the trustees and faculty of Bennington College.
      - American Dance Festival and School of Dance Planning, 1947-1957, 10 folders (Box 6)
      - Personal, 1948-1963, 1 folders (Box 6)
      - Placement and Recommendations, 1948-1952, 1 folders (Box 7)
      - Professional Activities, 1948-1969, 4 folders (Box 6)
      - Teaching Materials, circa 1942, 1 folders (Box 6)
    - Ruth Bloomer, circa 1924-1959 (Box 6)
      Ruth Bloomer had been a student at the first Bennington session and subsequently received her B.S. and M.A. degrees from New York University. She taught at the University of Oregon, the University of Michigan, and Denison University, and in 1945, she came to Connecticut College as the modern dance teacher. In 1953, with Martha Hill assuming "advisory" status, Bloomer assumed responsibility for the administration of the summer program. She resigned her position in 1958, but stated that she would remain a member of the advisory board.
      Contains personal writings, technique card examples, personal notes, costume designs, course materials, programs, correspondence, form letters, advertisements, newspaper clippings, telegrams, recommendations, resumes, jobs listings, administrative materials, publicity materials, and information on a 1957 conference for festival managers. Much of the correspondence to and from Bloomer regards job placements and recommendations. Her writings include pieces on a variety of subjects pertaining to dance including oriental dance, men and dancing, application of methods, the function of criticism and critics, and teacher training.
      - American Dance Festival, 1949-1959, 1 folders (Box 6)
      - Personal, 1952-1958, 1 folders (Box 6)
      - Placement and Recommendations, 1948-1959, 7 folders (Box 7)
      - Professional Activities, Writings, and Printed Materials circa 1924-1958, 9 folders (Box 6)
      - Teaching Materials, 1933-1944, 5 folders (Box 6)
    - Jeanette Schlottmann, circa 1959-1963 (Box 6)
      Jeanette Schlottmann had been a member of Anne Schley Duggan's modern dance group in Denton, TX. She received her M.A. in Denton at the Texas Woman's University and later joined its dance faculty. She taught there until 1950, when she moved to New York, studied with Jose Limon, Martha Graham, and Louis Horst, and found a position at Barnard College. In 1959, Schlottmann was appointed director of the Connecticut College School of the Dance and the American Dance Festival. One of her first decisions was to remove the "the" from the title and change the name to the Connecticut College School of Dance. In 1962, she established the summer touring company, Dance Advance, under the directorship of Janet Mansfield Soares. After the 1962 season, citing her marriage as a reason, Schlottmann resigned from Connecticut College and returned to Barnard College.
      Contains correspondence, job openings and application materials, resumes, form letters, programs, brochures and advertising materials, schedule for the 1959 Dance Teachers Guild Annual Convention, newspaper clippings, surveys, invitations, and telegrams.
      - American Dance Festival, 1959-1963, 5 folders (Box 6)
      - Personal, 1959-1963, 5 folders (Box 6)
      - Placement and Recommendations, 1959-1963, 5 folders (Box 7)
      - Professional Activities, 1959-1961, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Theodora Wiesner, circa 1963-1977 (Box 6)
      In 1930, Theodora Wiesner received her undergraduate degree from the University of Wisconsin in Madison. She moved to New York to do graduate work at New York University and then divided her time between her studies and teaching at various universities. She attended all but two of the Bennington summer sessions. After serving as a lieutenant commander in the U.S. Navy women's reserve during World War II, she returned to her studies on her doctorate, which she received in 1952. In 1949 she worked as an administrative assistant at the Connecticut College School of Dance. In 1950 she became director of the Dance program at Brooklyn College. With the 1962 retirement of Jeanette Schlottmann, the administrative board elected Wiesner director. In 1969, Wiesner recommended that a new director be appointed. In 1975, she retired from her directorship at Brooklyn College.
      Contains correspondence, job openings and application materials, resumes, form letters, invitations, newspaper clippings, brochures and advertising materials, schedules, surveys, and telegrams. Of interest is a 1963 letter from Charles Reinhart regarding his previous summer as executive director and 1964-1965 correspondence regarding the possibility of Balasaraswati appearing at the 1965 festival. Also present is a listing of Theodora Wiesner's duties as director of the festival and a letter from Wiesner to Oakes Ames, President of Connecticut College regarding her analysis of the question of ADF property ownership.
      - American Dance Festival, 1963-1977, 8 folders (Box 6)
      - Personal, 1964-1967, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - Placement and Recommendations, 1963-1969, 3 folders (Box 7)
      - Professional Activities, 1964-1967, 5 folders (Box 6)
    - Charles Reinhart, circa 1968-1977 (Box 6)
      After having spent several years in publicity, including at Jacob's Pillow in the summers of 1960 and 1961, Charles Reinhart opened a management office in 1962. Paul Taylor was one of his first major clients. In 1966, he helped establish the NEA's Dance Touring Program. He then ran the DTP for ten years. In 1968, Theodora Wiesner decided to resign control of the festival and recommended that a new director be appointed. The festival board and Connecticut College's administrative staff appointed Charles Reinhart. Reinhart also served as director of Jacob's Pillow in 1974.
      Contains correspondence, materials pertaining to a 1969 Performing Arts Aid Meeting, memos, form letters, information on the Harkness Memorial State Park submitted to the Connecticut Commission on the Arts, newspaper clippings, and resumes.
      - American Dance Festival, 1968-1977, 3 folders (Box 6)
      - Personal, 1968-1977, 1 folders (Box 6)
      - Placement and Recommendations, 1969-1977, 1 folders (Box 7)
      - Professional Activities, 1968-1977, 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Connecticut College, circa 1940-1981, 0.83 Linear Feet (Box 8)